unit 5a reading
exercise 2 page 70.
road safety technology a help or a
hindrance
in spite of today's highly sophisticated
road safety technology
road users still need to pay more
attention to basic road safety rules
high-tech roadside features include
solar powered cat size
and intelligent speed cameras as well as
cars which tell drivers to slow down if
they're going too fast nevertheless
people continue to get killed or injured
in road traffic accidents
on british roads alone statistics reveal
that the number of deaths rose to over 1
900 in 2011. what can possibly explain
this
in the first place the new road safety
technology can make drivers believe they
are safe
what happens is that the stress of
driving is replaced by boredom
because the gadgets take all the hard
work out of it
why worry about speed limits and maps
when you have access to electronic speed
control in gps
while these devices are designed to make
you feel safer research indicates that
they can in fact encourage risky
behavior
keep a calm and responsible eye on the
road and don't rely totally on your
gadgets
you will be much safer secondly even in
our high-tech age drivers still need to
stick to the rules of road safety
take for example seat belts it is still
as important as ever for drivers and
their passengers to wear them
in collisions an unbelted rear passenger
can kill or seriously injure the driver
or front seat passenger
avoiding the use of a mobile phone while
driving is equally important
statistics show that drivers speaking on
mobiles have reaction times fifty
percent
slower than that of normal drivers they
are also four times more likely to have
a crash
another problem is fatigue which is one
of the biggest factors in more than ten
percent of car accidents
drivers should take a 15 minute break
for every two hours they drive
one final point is that pedestrians also
take unnecessary risks
while trying to cross the road for
instance they may rely solely on
flashing signs
automated vocal instructions or
in-pavement lighting
to get across safely pedestrians should
also be aware of the safest place to
cross the road
whether it's a zebra crossing a traffic
light crossing or a footbridge
even walking a little further is still
safer than crossing through moving
traffic
if you have no choice but to cross
between part cars place yourself between
the parked cars
that will give you a good view of the
road and the parked vehicles will
protect you from moving vehicles
it is obvious that while driving and
road systems will become even more
high-tech in the future
this is not enough to guarantee you are
safe on the road
drivers and pedestrians alike must also
stick to the rules
after all can the increasing array of
safety features in cars and on the
streets ever replace the most important
safety features of all
a responsible driver and a self-aware
pedestrian